A Guide to the Wickham Family Papers, 1766-1945
Virginia Historical Society
Additional records of William Fanning Wickham consist of accounts, 1893-1897; materials as colonel commanding the First Cavalry Regiment of Virginia Volunteers (general and special orders, invitations to participate in special events, expenses of a court-martial, and subscribers to the Albemarle Light Horse Troop of Virginia Volunteers); invitations and notices of meetings of such secret societies, clubs, and fraternal orders as the Scottish Rite Freemasons, Shriners, Knights Templar, Tuckahoe Farmers' Club, and Wednesday Club of Richmond. General miscellany includes records of his law practice; assorted materials concerning the construction of St. Paul's Church in Hanover County; materials concerning the Seay Farm in Powhatan County; Republican Party materials; records of the University of Virginia alumni banquet in Richmond, 1894; bonds; and materials concerning Hanover County courthouse.
Series 12 contains materials relating to Julia Wickham Porcher (1860-1933), who married her cousin Thomas Ashby Wickham in 1897 and lived at "Woodside." She kept a diary (Box 28) in 1896 during a trip to England and France that contains numerous clippings and photographs along with daily notations. Her correspondence, 1870-1929, is primarily with Porcher family members and with friends, but also includes letters from a number of French soldiers and widows during and just after World War I. Among the significant correspondents: Hobart Asquith (concerning his Confederate serve in the Maryland Line under generals Lunsford Lindsay Lomax and Williams Carter Wickham), Episcopal clergyman Ambler Mason Blackford, French clergyman C. Boyer (written in French at the close of World War I), New York banker Charles Meriwether Fry, Elizabeth (Leigh) Fry, Hamilton Wright Mable, Virginia Carter Minor, Alexander Mazyck Porcher, Isabella Sarah (Peyre) Porcher, Virginia Leigh Porcher, Dr. Walter Peyre Porcher, Helen Willis (Minor) Poyntz, Conway Robinson (concerning President Rutherford B. Hayes), Mary Susan Selden (Leigh) Robinson, Irish actress Patricia (Collinge) Smith, Littleton Maclurg Wickham, and Bishop Richard Hooker Wilmer (enclosing a copy of his pamphlet entitled Some Thoughts on Robert Elsmere, in a Letter to a Friend [1889?]).Mrs. Wickham's account books include a volume covering expenses on a trip to Europe in 1891 and a passbook apparently on a New York bank, 1895-1896. Then follow in Boxes 33-34 her very extensive collection of autographs of famous persons. Mrs. Wickham apparently began collecting as a young woman with her father's encouragement and aid, and amassed a fine group of letters, autographs, and clipped signatures from her father's friends and medical associates, as well as from other Porcher and Wickham family members. The first volume remains intact and an index to it follows this collection description. Loose items have been filed in the same box with the album, as the index will show. The second volume was in very poor condition, the highly acidic paper on which many items were pasted threatened their very existence. The volume thus was disassembled and the loose items filed alphabetically according to type of document. A separate index of the documents removed from this second volume is also available.
The remaining materials of Mrs. Wickham in this collection include a scrapbook dating from 1904 containing numerous newspaper clippings, and a large file of clippings grouped around certain subjects (obituary notices, Virginia and South Carolina local history, Huguenots in America, general information). Miscellany consists of a few accounts, 1920-1926; an essay on women; a student notebook (primarily concerns literature and language); materials concerning the "Half-Hour Reading Club," 1889-1895, presumably in South Carolina; genealogical and historical notes; and lines of verse by Edmund Pendleton.
Series 13 is made up of a few surviving papers of Judge Thomas Ashby Wickham's brother Littleton Tazewell Wickham survive in this collection. They consist of correspondence, 1880-1889; accounts, 1886-1888; account books (two volumes), 1878-1883, 1882-1883; and a check stub book, 1882-1884. Series 14 contains papers of their sister Elizabeth (Wickham) Fitzhugh, including letters, 1866-1881, from Thomas Ashby, Mary Louise Brooks, Isabella Sarah (Peyre) Porcher, William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880) and others; accounts, 1882-1884; and miscellany. A number of items of correspondence, 1882-1939, of Mrs. Wickham's sister Virginia Leigh Porcher, make up Series 15. These may be found in Box 36 as well.
Littleton Maclurg Wickham (1898-1973), son of Judge Thomas Ashby Wickham, represents the last generation of "Woodside Wickhams" in this collection. His papers are contained in Series 16. His correspondence, 1909-1945, is primarily with family and friends from the University of Virginia and concerns in part Zeta Psi Fraternity of North America and Wickham's service in World War I. Correspondents include John Herbert Claiborne, Richard Hartwell Cocke (of "Lower Bremo," Fluvanna County, and as an attorney in Alabama), Richard Davenport Gilliam, Congreeman Andrew Jackson Montague, Amelia Louise (Rives) Chanler Troubetzkoy and Dr. Frederick Henry Wilke.
Records of Littleton Wickham's days at the Episcopal High School in Alexandria, both as student and teacher, may be found in Box 37. Examination reports, exam questions, a list of students, invitations and programs illustrate his career as a student, 1911-1915, while teach contracts (signed by Archibald Robinson Hoxton) and accounts cover his teaching career, 1917-1921 (see also his correspondence with his mother, Julia Wickham (Porcher) Wickham). Wickham attended the University of Virginia, graduating from the college in 1917 and attending the School of Law from 1922 to 1924. Examination reports, a recommendation from Professor Richard Henry Wilson, and miscellany cover his years in Charlottesville. Miscellany concerns his World War I service (1917) and personal accounts, 1923-1938.
The collection closes with Series 17, which contains miscellaneous family and non-family materials including letters written to or by Anne Alston Porcher, Margaret Ward Porcher and Ashby Porcher Wickham; a commonplace book of Mary Charlotte Porcher, 1850; and accounts of Julia Porcher (Wickham) Porter, 1931-1937.
Arrangement
Arranged into seventeen series by main entry and further subdivided by document type or subject as necessary.
Index Terms
Ashby, Thomas, 1783-1872.; Autograph albums -- Virginia -- Richmond.; Bunker Hill (Darlington County, S.C.); Diaries -- Virginia -- Henrico County -- History -- 20th century.; East Tuckahoe (Henrico County, Va.); Lawyers -- Virginia -- Richmond -- History.; New Orleans (La.) -- History -- 19th century.; Physicians -- South Carolina -- Charleston -- History -- 19th century.; Porcher, Francis Peyre, 1825-1895.; Practice of law -- Louisiana -- New Orleans -- History -- 19th century.; Practice of law -- Virginia - - Richmond -- History.; Sprague (Wash.) -- History -- 19th century.; Tazewell, Littleton Waller, 1774-1860.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1783-1865.; Veterans -- France -- History -- World War, 1914-1918.; Virginia -- Description and travel -- 19th century.; Virginia. General Assembly. Senate -- Members -- History -- 20th century.; Virginia. Militia. Cavalry Regiment, 1st (1891-1897); Wickham, Elizabeth Selden Maclurg, 1815-1853.; Wickham family.; Wickham, John, 1763-1839.; Wickham, Julia Wickham Porcher, 1860-1933.; Wickham, Littleton Waller Tazewell, 1821- 1909.; Wickham, Thomas Ashby, 1857-1939.; Wickham, William Fanning, 1860- 1900.; Woodside (Henrico County, Va.)
Contents List
- John Wickham (1763-1839), Richmond and "East Tuckahoe," Henrico County, Va.
  - Correspondence, 1798-1839 (Box 1-2)
  - Law materials and miscellany, 1766-1833 (Box 3)
    Law practice, 1766-1833; Burr trial, 1806-1807; "East Tuckahoe" materials; commonplace book; miscellany; estate.
- Elizabeth Selden (McClurg) Wickham (1781-1853), Richmond, Va. (Box 4)
  Correspondence, 1794-1850; wills of benefactors; miscellany.
- Maclurg Wickham (1814-1900), "East Tuckahoe," Henrico County, Va. (Box 5)
  Diary, 1851-1882; correspondence, 1848-1876; accounts, 1860-1897; bonds; Wickham v. Graham materials; miscellany; estate.
- Littleton Waller Tazewell Wickham (1821-1909), New Orleans, La., and "Woodside," Henrico County, Va.
  - Correspondence, 1836-1897. (Box 5 (cont.)-8)
  - Financial materials, 1849-1891. (Box 8 (cont.)-10)
    Account books, bank books, loose accounts, bonds and notes.
  - University of Virginia records, 1837-1839. (Box 10 (cont.))
  - Law practice, 1848-1852. (Box 10 (cont.))
  - Plantation records, "Woodside" and "Bunker Hill," 1858-1861. (Box 10 (cont.)-11)
  - Miscellany (Box 11 (cont.))
    Civil War materials, 1862-1865; bankruptcy materials, 1859-1880; miscellany.
- Eliza Wyckoff (Nicholson) Wickham (d. 1850), New Orleans, La. (Box 12)
  Correspondence, 1846-1850; accounts, 1849-1850; estate of John Nicholson, 1842-1851; miscellany; estate.
- Elizabeth Peyre (Ashby) Laurens Wickham (1824-1859), Charleston, S.C. and Richmond, Va. (Box 12 (cont.))
  Letters to, 1852-1859; letters of her mother, Elizabeth (Peyre) Sinkler Ashby, 1821-1831.
- John Wickham (1825-1902), "Woodside," Henrico County, Va. (Box 13)
  Correspondence, 1837-1902; accounts, 1876-1877, 1893-1902; "East Tuckahoe" materials, 1840-1868; bankruptcy materials, 1878-1896; miscellany and estate.
- Remaining children of John Wickham (1763-1839).
- Doctor Francis Peyre Porcher (1824-1895), Charleston, S.C.
  - Correspondence and lectures, 1864-1895. (Box 14)
  - Porcher family materials, 1864-1883, and miscellany. (Box 15)
- Thomas Ashby Wickham (1857-1939), Sprague, Washington, Richmond, and "Woodside," Henrico County, Va. (Box 13)
  - Diaries, 1900, 1902-1925, 1929-1939 (Box 15 (cont.)-19)
  - Correspondence, 1872-1938 (Box Box 19 (cont.)-20)
  - Financial materials, 1882-1939 (Box 21)
    Accounts, 1882-1885, 1895-1922 (sporadic), 1930-1939; check stub books (2 v.), 1910-1912, 1912-1914.
  - Plantation materials, 1894-1935 (Box 22)
    "Woodside" materials, 1894-1935; land records, 1900-1912
  - Legal and political materials, 1843-1921, and miscellany. (Box 22 (cont.))
    Law practice, 1843-1921; Virginia Senate, 1908; Democratic Congressional primary, 1910; miscellany.
- William Fanning Wickham (1860-1900), Richmond, Va.
  - Correspondence, 1891-1897. (Box 23-26)
  - Financial materials, 1893-1897. (Box 27)
  - Military, 1893-1894, personal, and general miscellany. (Box 27 (cont.))
    First Cavalry Regiment material, 1893-1894; secret societies, clubs, fraternal orders; general miscellany.
- Julia Wickham (Porcher) Wickham (1860-1933), Charleston, S.C., and "Woodside," Henrico County, Va.
  - Julia Wickham Diary, 1896 (Box 28)
  - Correspondence, 1870-1929. (Box 28 (cont.)-32)
  - Account books, 1891, 1895-1896 (Box 33)
  - Autograph albums, 1769-1887 (Box 33 (cont.)-34)
    Autograph album I, 1769-1887; Aautograph album II, 1825-1884
  - Scrapbook and miscellany. (Box 35)
    Scrapbook, 1904; newspaper clippings; miscellany.
- Littleton Tazewell Wickham (1858-1890), "Woodside," Henrico County, Va. (Box 36)
  Correspondence, 1880-1889; accounts, 1886-1888; account books (2 vols.), 1878-1883, 1882-1883; check stub book, 1882-1884.
- Elizabeth (Wickham) Fitzhugh (1854-1889), "Woodside," Henrico County, Va. (Box 36 (cont.))
  Letters to, 1866-1881; accounts, 1882-1884; miscellany
- Virginia Leigh Porcher (1866-1940), Charleston, S.C., and "Woodside," Henrico County, Va. (Box 36 (cont.))
  Correspondence, 1882-1939
- Littleton Maclurg Wickham (1898-1973), "Woodside," Henrico County, Va.
  - Correspondence, 1909-1945 (Box 36 (cont.)-37)
  - Educational materials and miscellany (Box 37 (cont.))
    Episcopal High School records; University of Virginia; miscellany
- Miscellaneous family and non-family materials (Box 37 (cont.))
  Letters, commonplace book, accounts